<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Bioinformatics | John Ramey]]></title>
  <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/categories/bioinformatics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ramhiser.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-14T21:54:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ramhiser.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Ramey]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[johnramey@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 2 Solutions - Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/chapter-2-solutions-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T20:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/chapter-2-solutions-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I have mentioned previously, I have begun reading <a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU">Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics by Ewens and Grant</a> and working selected problems for each chapter. In this post, I will give my solution to two problems. The first problem is pretty straightforward.</p>

<h2>Problem 2.20</h2>

<blockquote><p>Suppose that a parent of genetic type <em>Mm</em> has three children. Then the parent transmits the <em>M</em> gene to each child with probability 1/2, and the genes that are transmitted to each of the three children are independent. Let $I_1 = 1$ if children 1 and 2 had the same gene transmitted, and $I_1 = 0$ otherwise. Similarly, let $I_2 = 1$ if children 1 and 3 had the same gene transmitted, $I_2 = 0$ otherwhise, and let $I_3 = 1$ if children 2 and 3 had the same gene transmitted, $I_3 = 0$ otherwise.</p></blockquote>

<h2>Problems 2.23 - 2.27</h2>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Textbook - Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/textbook-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T20:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/textbook-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of my effort to acquaint myself more with biology, bioinformatics, and statistical genetics, I am trying to find as many resources as I can that provide a solid foundation. For instance, I am wading through <a href="http://amzn.to/Mx5jCm">Molecular Biology of the Cell</a> at a pace of about 10-15 pages per day -- this takes nearly an hour every day.</p>

<p>I am also going through <a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU">Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics by Ewens and Grant</a> and working selected problems for each chapter. My intention is to post my solutions to these chapter exercises. Thus far, I have made it through the first three chapters, and I will begin posting my solutions soon. I am interested particularly in problems regarding statistical topics with which I have little-to-no experience and also topics where I lack intuition regarding the biological applications.</p>

<p>Here is a thumbnail of the book:</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/41UT3fUB%2BKL._BO2,204,203,200_PIsitb-sticker-arrow-click,TopRight,35,-76_AA300_SH20_OU01_.jpg" alt="Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics Textbook" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
