<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Statistics | John Ramey]]></title>
  <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/categories/statistics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ramhiser.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-08-15T07:50:20-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://ramhiser.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[John Ramey]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[johnramey@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Chapter 2 Solutions - Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/chapter-2-solutions-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T20:42:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/chapter-2-solutions-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I have mentioned previously, I have begun reading <a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU">Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics by Ewens and Grant</a> and working selected problems for each chapter. In this post, I will give my solution to two problems. The first problem is pretty straightforward.</p>

<h2 id="problem-220">Problem 2.20</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Suppose that a parent of genetic type <em>Mm</em> has three children. Then the parent transmits the <em>M</em> gene to each child with probability 1/2, and <strong>the genes that are transmitted to each of the three children are independent</strong>. Let <script type="math/tex">I_1 = 1</script> if children 1 and 2 had the same gene transmitted, and <script type="math/tex">I_1 = 0</script> otherwise. Similarly, let <script type="math/tex">I_2 = 1</script> if children 1 and 3 had the same gene transmitted, <script type="math/tex">I_2 = 0</script> otherwhise, and let <script type="math/tex">I_3 = 1</script> if children 2 and 3 had the same gene transmitted, <script type="math/tex">I_3 = 0</script> otherwise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The question first asks us to how that the three random variables are pairwise independent but not independent. The pairwise independence comes directly from the bolded phrase in the problem statement. Now, to show that the three random variables are not independent, denote by <script type="math/tex">p_j</script> the probability that <script type="math/tex">I_j = 1</script>, <script type="math/tex">j = 1, 2, 3</script>. If we had independence, then the following statement would be true:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
P(I_1 = 1, I_2 = 1, I_3 = 0) = p_1 p_2 (1 - p_3).
</script>

<p>However, notice that the event in the lefthand side can never happen because if <script type="math/tex">I_1 = 1</script> and <script type="math/tex">I_2 = 1</script>, then <script type="math/tex">I_3</script> must be 1. Hence, the lefthand side must equal 0, while the righthand side equals 1/8. Therefore, the three random variables are not independent.</p>

<p>The question also asks us to discuss why the variance of <script type="math/tex">I_1 + I_2 + I_3</script> is equal to the sum of the individual variances. Often, this is only the case of the random variables are independent. But because the random variables here are pairwise independent, the covariances must be 0. Thus, the equality must hold.</p>

<h2 id="problems-223---227">Problems 2.23 - 2.27</h2>

<p>While I worked the above problem because of its emphasis on genetics, the following set of problems is much more fun in terms of the mathematics because of its usage of approximations.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For <script type="math/tex">i = 1, \ldots, n</script>, let <script type="math/tex">X_i</script> be the <script type="math/tex">i</script>th lifetime of certain cellular proteins until degradation. We assume that <script type="math/tex">X_1, \ldots, X_n</script> are iid random variables, each of which is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_distribution">exponentially distributed</a> with rate parameter <script type="math/tex">\lambda > 0</script>. Furthermore, let <script type="math/tex">n = 2m + 1</script> be an odd integer.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This set of questions is concerned with the mean and variance of the sample median, <script type="math/tex">X_{(m + 1)}</script>, where <script type="math/tex">X_{(i)}</script> denotes the <script type="math/tex">i</script>th <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Order_statistic">order statistic</a>. First, note that the mean and variance of the minimum value <script type="math/tex">X_{(1)}</script> are <script type="math/tex">1/(n\lambda)</script> and <script type="math/tex">1/(n\lambda)^2</script>, respectively. From the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memorylessness#The_memoryless_distributions_are_the_exponential_distributions">memoryless property</a> of the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_distribution">exponential distribution</a>, the mean value of the time until the next protein degrades is independent of the previous. However, there are now <script type="math/tex">n - 1</script> proteins remaining. Thus, the mean and variance of <script type="math/tex">X_{(2)}</script> are <script type="math/tex">1/(n\lambda) + 1/((n-1)\lambda)</script> and <script type="math/tex">1/(n\lambda)^2 + 1/((n-1)\lambda)^2</script>, respectively. Continuining in this manner, we have</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
E[X_{(m + 1)}] = \frac{1}{(2m + 1)\lambda} + \frac{1}{(2m)\lambda} + \ldots + \frac{1}{(m + 1)\lambda}
</script>

<p>and</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
Var[X_{(m + 1)}] = \frac{1}{(2m + 1)^2\lambda^2} + \frac{1}{(2m)^2\lambda^2} + \ldots + \frac{1}{(m + 1)^2\lambda^2}.
</script>

<p>Now, we wish to approximate the mean with a much simpler formula. First, from (B.7) in Appendix B, we have</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">
\sum_{k=1}^n \approx \log n + \gamma,
</script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex">\gamma</script> is <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler%E2%80%93Mascheroni_constant">Euler’s constant</a>. Then, we can write the expected sample median as</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display">% &lt;![CDATA[

E[X_{(m + 1)}] &= \frac{1}{\lambda} \sum_{k=m+1}^{2m+1} \frac{1}{k}\\
&= \frac{1}{\lambda} \left(\sum_{k=1}^{2m+1} \frac{1}{k} - \sum_{k=1}^{m} \frac{1}{k} \right)\\
&\approx \frac{1}{\lambda} \left( \log (2m + 1) + \gamma - \log m - \gamma)\\
&= \frac{1}{\lambda} \log \left(2 + \frac{1}{m}).
 %]]&gt;</script>

<p>Hence, as <script type="math/tex">n \rightarrow \infty</script>, this approximation goes to <script type="math/tex"> \frac{\log 2}{\lambda}</script>, which is the median of an exponentially distributed random variable. Specifically, the median is the solution to <script type="math/tex">F_X(x) = 1/2</script>, where <script type="math/tex">F_X</script> denotes the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumulative_distribution_function">cumulative distribution function</a> of the random variable <script type="math/tex">X</script>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Textbook - Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/textbook-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-14T20:17:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2012/08/14/textbook-statistical-methods-in-bioinformatics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of my effort to acquaint myself more with biology, bioinformatics, and statistical genetics, I am trying to find as many resources as I can that provide a solid foundation. For instance, I am wading through <a href="http://amzn.to/Mx5jCm">Molecular Biology of the Cell</a> at a pace of about 10-15 pages per day – this takes nearly an hour every day.</p>

<p>I am also going through <a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU">Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics by Ewens and Grant</a> and working selected problems for each chapter. My intention is to post my solutions to these chapter exercises. Thus far, I have made it through the first three chapters, and I will begin posting my solutions soon. I am interested particularly in problems regarding statistical topics with which I have little-to-no experience and also topics where I lack intuition regarding the biological applications.</p>

<p>Here is a thumbnail of the book:</p>

<p><a href="http://amzn.to/PiXCiU"><img src="http://ecx.images-amazon.com/images/I/41UT3fUB%2BKL._BO2,204,203,200_PIsitb-sticker-arrow-click,TopRight,35,-76_AA300_SH20_OU01_.jpg" alt="Statistical Methods in Bioinformatics Textbook" /></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Listing of Statistics and Machine Learning Conferences]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2011/06/12/listing-of-statistics-and-machine-learning-conferences/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-12T17:20:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2011/06/12/listing-of-statistics-and-machine-learning-conferences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Occasionally, I will query Google with “statistics conferences”, “machine learning conferences” or “pattern recognition conferences” and the like. But often, it is difficult to obtain anything
meaningful other than the conferences of which I’m already aware (such as JSM, ICML, some IEEE conferences). Today, I found <a href="http://www.wikicfp.com/cfp/">WikiCFP</a>, which is a <strong>A Wiki for Calls for
Papers</strong>. This seems to be what I needed. In particular, the following are very useful to me:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://www.wikicfp.com/cfp/call?conference=machine%20learning">Machine Learning on WikiCFP</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://www.wikicfp.com/cfp/call?conference=statistics">Statistics on WikiCFP</a></li>
</ul>

<p>It seems limited for statistics though, as JSM is not even listed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started with Some Baseball Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramhiser.com/blog/2011/05/24/getting-started-with-some-baseball-data/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-24T21:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramhiser.com/blog/2011/05/24/getting-started-with-some-baseball-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>With all of the discussions (hype?) regarding applied statistics, machine learning, and data science, I have been looking for a go-to source of data unrelated to my day-to-day work. I loved baseball as
a kid. I love baseball now. I love baseball stats. Why not do a grown-up version of what I used to do when I spent hours staring at and memorizing baseball stats on the back of a few pieces of cardboard
on which I spent my allowance?</p>

<p>To get started, I purchased a copy of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Baseball-Hacks-Joseph-Adler/dp/0596009429/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1306290220&amp;sr=8-1">Baseball Hacks</a>. The author suggests the usage of MySQL,
so I will oblige. First, I downloaded some baseball data in MySQL format on my web server (Ubuntu 10.04) and decompressed it; when I downloaded the data, it was timestamped as 28 March 2011, so
double-check if there is an updated version.</p>

<p><code>bash
mkdir baseball
cd baseball
wget http://www.baseball-databank.org/files/BDB-sql-2011-03-28.sql.zip
unzip BDB-sql-2011-03-28.sql.zip
</code></p>

<p>Next, in MySQL I created a user named <strong>baseball</strong>, a database entitled <strong>bbdatabank</strong> and granted all privileges on this database to the user <strong>baseball</strong>. To do this, first open MySQL as root:</p>

<p><code>bash
mysql -u root -p
</code></p>

<p>At the MySQL prompt, type: (Note the tick marks (`) around <strong>bbdatabank</strong> when granting privileges.)</p>

<p><code>sql
CREATE USER 'baseball'@'localhost' IDENTIFIED BY 'YourPassword';
CREATE database bbdatabank;
GRANT ALL PRIVILEGES ON `bbdatabank`.* TO 'baseball'@'localhost';
FLUSH PRIVILEGES;
quit
</code></p>

<p>Finally, we read the data into the database we just created by:</p>

<p><code>bash
mysql -u baseball -p -s bbdatabank &lt; BDB-sql-2011-03-28.sql
</code></p>

<p>That’s it! Most of this code has been adapted from <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Baseball-Hacks-Joseph-Adler/dp/0596009429/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1306290220&amp;sr=8-1">Baseball Hacks</a>, although I’ve tweaked a
couple of things. As I progress through the book, I will continue to add interesting finds and code as posts. Eventually, I will move away from the book’s code as it focuses too much on the
“Intro to Data Exploration” reader with constant mentions of MS Access/Excel. The author means well though as he urges the reader to use *nix/Mac OS X.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
